(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-08-24T10:25:36.302589",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
私、湊あくあ！
I'm Minato Aqua!
職業スーパーウルトラなんでもパーフェクトなメイドさん！
A super-ultra all-round perfect maid by trade!
今日もご主人様のために精一杯がんばっちゃうぞー！
Today, I'll do my absolute best for my Master too!
あくたんのこと好きすぎ☆リング
I love Akutan way too much☆-ring!
天才こまめいどはてんてこ舞い
This genius little maid is running ragged,
お料理焦がしたなんてへへっぺろ 許してご主人様っ
burning the food, "Hehe, blep!" Forgive me, Master!
ゲームばかりして怒られている
Getting scolded for playing games all day,
プリティーネコフェイスでごまかすにゃん
I brush it off with a pretty cat face, Nyan!
お昼寝は メイドのサガ
Afternoon naps are a maid's destiny,
ご機嫌な夢見てスヤヤヤ
having a happy dream, Zzz...
エプロン着用者は反省中？
Is the apron-wearer reflecting on her actions?
遠出はいかないよアイドルメイド
No going far away, I'm an idol maid!
ああ ご主人様にビビッときてる
Ah, I'm electrified by my Master!
ごめんねメイド 服ぬいだら
Sorry, Maid! Once I take off my uniform,
だらだらの女だけどご主人度思い出作れますか
I'm just a lazy girl, but can we make memories with my Masterness?
もっと仲良くしてね はげまし見ないで
Get closer with me, don't look away,
しばくぞになりあたって思い出してくれないよねこの
I'll beat you up, so don't you dare forget this...
あくたんのこと好きすぎ☆リング
I love Akutan way too much☆-ring!
混合こまめいどは寝不足 朝から晩までやることだらけ
This mixed-up little maid is sleep-deprived, chores from morning till night!
歌って踊ってドタバタ 団子まがってご主人様っ
Singing, dancing, bustling, rolling around, Master!
レアをやぶ は止めないけど 猫耳のても借りてがんばるにゃん
I won't stop the rare breaks, but with cat-ear paws I'll do my best, Nyan!
おかえりなさい ご主人様っ たまにはサービスいいでしょっ
Welcome back, Master! A service treat once in a while is nice, right?
ゲームに負けたら６項のコメント たのしんでいたらお仕置きね
If I lose a game, six-paragraph comments; if I have too much fun, it's punishment!
あれ ご主人様おこったの？
Huh, Master, are you mad?
ねぇどう服を着たら わがままな女の子になる
Hey, what kind of outfit makes me a spoiled girl?
月曜日は体が動かない
On Mondays, my body just won't move,
ていうか毎日でした。ピリピリ偏頭痛
I mean, it's every day. Throbbing migraine.
起き出したらメイドのくせして お料理ダメ
When I wake up, being a maid, I'm bad at cooking,
掃除もちょっとあれ てんてこ舞い舞いで
cleaning is a bit... running around in circles,
まいったうーん…精進あるのみですね
what a mess... I just need to devote myself.
へいゆー。会いたくなってしまったな今夜も
Hey you. I've grown to want to see you again tonight,
夜な夜な集まって何する？
gathering night after night, what do we do?
月火水木金土日 365日
Mon, Tue, Wed, Thu, Fri, Sat, Sun, 365 days,
画面越しご挨拶
greetings through the screen.
スキだっちゃ。って言っちゃったって全然可愛くない
I like you. Even if I say that, it's not cute at all.
勝手に凹んで泣いてみてって全然可愛くない
Sulking and crying on my own isn't cute at all.
君だって同じダメよりの人種です
You're the same kind of hopeless person too,
そんな優しくして…あたしに気があるのかな？
being so gentle... could you be interested in me?
もうこんな時間どんな予感 神ハプニング
Already this time, what kind of premonition, a god-tier happening.
ああ中毒症状 依存度マックス メンタル崩壊
Ah, withdrawal symptoms, max dependency, mental breakdown.
あなたののことをもっともっと知りたい
I want to know more and more about you.
壊れたテレビは叩けば直る
A broken TV can be fixed by hitting it.
血圧やば。一緒に寝てよ大人さん
Blood pressure's dangerous. Sleep with me, grown-up!
お迎えさん 世界の皆さんおまえさん
Escorts, everyone in the world, you guys,
銀河一のラブを込めて行くよせーの
sending out the galaxy's best love, ready, go!
おいしくなれ もえもえきゅーん
Make it delicious, moe moe kyun!
水曜日は意識がレボリューション
On Wednesdays, consciousness is in revolution,
ていうか毎日でした。ピリピリ偏頭痛
I mean, it's every day. Throbbing migraine.
あたしったら競争社会不適合者？
Am I an unfit for competitive society?
でも挙動は適合者のフリして暴言はいて…うーんヘコむんだ。
But my behavior pretends to fit in while spewing harsh words... ugh.
これって放送事故？
Is this a broadcasting accident?
へいゆー。会いたくなってしまったな今夜も
Hey you. I've grown to want to see you again tonight,
自己嫌悪からの脱却
breaking free from self-loathing,
頑張れ私負けない！
Do your best, me, don't lose!
月火水木金土日 365日
Mon, Tue, Wed, Thu, Fri, Sat, Sun, 365 days,
画面越しご挨拶
greetings through the screen.
スキだっちゃ。って言っちゃったって全然可愛くない
I like you. Even if I say that, it's not cute at all.
勝手に凹んで泣いてみてって全然可愛くない
Sulking and crying on my own isn't cute at all.
君だって同じダメよりの人種です
You're the same kind of hopeless person too,
どれだけ優しくする…私のこと好きなの？
being so gentle... do you like me?
もうこんな時間どんな予感 神ハプニング
Already this time, what kind of premonition, a god-tier happening.
ああ中毒症状 依存度マックス メンタル崩壊
Ah, withdrawal symptoms, max dependency, mental breakdown.
あなたののことをもっともっと知りたい
I want to know more and more about you.
まだあなたのことを何にも知らない
I still know nothing about you.
ていうか休日は身体が動きません
On holidays, my body just won't move,
ていうか毎日でした。ピリピリ偏頭痛
I mean, it's every day. Throbbing migraine.
あたしったらメイドのくせしてお料理ダメ 掃除もちょっとあれ
Being a maid, I'm bad at cooking, cleaning is a bit...
てんてこ舞いでまいったお掃除あるのみですね
running around in circles... I just need to clean.
へいゆー。会いたくなってしまったな今夜も
Hey you. I've grown to want to see you again tonight,
宵の夜なような集まって何する？
gathering night after night, what do we do?
金土日 365日 画面越しご挨拶
Fri, Sat, Sun, 365 days, greetings through the screen.
スキだっちゃ。って言っちゃったって全然可愛くない
I like you. Even if I say that, it's not cute at all.
勝手に凹んで泣いてみてって全然可愛くない
Sulking and crying on my own isn't cute at all.
勝手に凹んで泣いてみてって全然可愛くない 君だって同じ
Sulking and crying isn't cute at all. You're the same,
ダメよりの自由です。そんな優しくして
more towards hopeless freedom. Being so gentle,
私に気があるのかな？もうこんな時間
could you be interested in me? Already this time,
どんな予感 神ハプニング ああ中毒症状
what kind of premonition, a god-tier happening, withdrawal symptoms.
依存度マックス メンタル崩壊 あなたのことを
Max dependency, mental breakdown, about you,
もっともっと知りたい。
I want to know more and more.
金曜日は意識がレボリューション
On Fridays, consciousness is in revolution,
ていうか毎日でした。ピリピリ偏頭痛 あたしったら
I mean, it's every day. Throbbing migraine, as for me,
京都社会不適合者？でも挙動は適応者のふりして暴言はいて
unfit for society? But my behavior pretends to fit in, spewing harsh words,
へこんでこれって放送事故？へいゆー！
feeling down, is this a broadcast accident? Hey you!
会いたくなってしまったな 今夜も自己嫌悪からの脱却
I want to see you tonight too, breaking free from self-loathing.
限界オタクの魂胆が聞こえるよ
I can hear the scheme of a limit-breaking otaku.
頑張れ私負けない！
Do your best, me, don't lose!
スキだっちゃ。って言っちゃったって全然可愛くない
I like you. Even if I say that, it's not cute at all.
勝手に凹んで泣いてみてって全然可愛くない
Sulking and crying on my own isn't cute at all.
君だって同じダメよりの自由です
You're the same, more towards hopeless freedom.
どれだけ優しくする？私のこと好きなのかな？
Being so gentle, could you like me?
もうこんな時間どんな予感 神ハプニング
Already this time, what kind of premonition, a god-tier happening.
ああ中毒症状 依存度マックス メンタル崩壊
Ah, withdrawal symptoms, max dependency, mental breakdown.
あなたのことをもっともっと知りたい
I want to know more and more about you.
私のことももっともっと知って欲しい
I want you to know more and more about me too.
ああ 特別じゃない 私のこと勘違いして…
Ah, don't misunderstand me as someone special...
馬鹿ね…鳴れ愛こそが 君と僕を繋ぐ光
How foolish... ring out, for love is the light connecting you and me.
月火水木金土日 365日
Mon, Tue, Wed, Thu, Fri, Sat, Sun, 365 days,
画面越しご挨拶
greetings through the screen.
スキだっちゃ。って言っちゃったって全然可愛くない
I like you. Even if I say that, it's not cute at all.
勝手に凹んで泣いてみてって全然可愛くない
Sulking and crying on my own isn't cute at all.
今日は4周年ライブに遊びに来てくれてありがとう！
Thank you for coming to play at my 4th anniversary live today!
え？もう4周年ってマジ？
Wait, is it really 4 years already?!
いっぱいゲストも出るから
Lots of guests will be appearing,
よかったら最後まで観てねー！
so please watch until the very end!
水も金同日 365日
Wednesday, Friday, Saturday, Sunday, 365 days,
ダメーンごしごしあいさつ
No-no, scrubbing greetings,
こわくあーせーの！
Scary Aqua—ready, go!
スキになっちゃって いっちゃったって 全然可愛くない
Saying "I love you" and blurting it out is not cute at all.
拗ねていじけたって 泣いてみたって 全然可愛くない
Pouting and sulking, or trying to cry, is not cute at all.
君だって同じ ダメ男の自習です
You're the same, it's study hall for hopeless guys.
音楽優しくするのも 私のコト好きだからっ
Making the music gentle is also because you love me!
モーコンナジカン ドンナヨカン カミハプニング
Already this time, what a premonition, a divine happening,
アーチュードクシャショウ イドンデマスクス メンタルホウカイ
Ah, acute poisoning show, challenging masks, mental breakdown.
あなたのコトをもっともっと知りたい
I want to know more and more about you.
まだあなたのコトをなにも知らない
I still know nothing about you.
Kiss me baby
ありがとうございましたー！
Thank you very much!
ありがとうございました！2曲続けてお聴きいただきましたー！
Thank you! You've listened to two songs back-to-back!
えー、あくたんのこと好きすぎソング そしてあいわなでした！
That was the "Aqua-tan Super Love Song" and "Aiwana"!
ありがとう！
Thank you!
ということで、あくすきなんかめっちゃあいのていたけどね なんか賑やかな感じになってたけど
So, for "Akusuki", there were a lot of call-and-responses, right? It felt really lively,
みんなはコメントでちゃんとあいのてしてくれたー？
but did you guys properly do the call-and-responses in the comments?
じゃあ一回ちょっと聴くからみんなねあのコメントしてください それではいくよ！
Now, I'll listen for a second, so everyone please leave comments! Here we go!
あくたんのことを…好きすぎー！
Saying... "I love Aqua-tan so much!"
みんなありがとー ありがとございました！ありがとうございます！
Thanks everyone! Thank you very much! Thank you!
ということで、なんと4周年 わー！4周年ライブですよ もう4周年ですか あくあ色フェスティバルということで
So, amazingly, it's our 4th anniversary! Wow! It's a 4th-anniversary live. Is it already 4 years? As the Aqua-Iro Festival,
フェスティバルと言うからにはねお祭りのようななんかねたくさんのゲストがこの先出る予感がしますが
since it's called a festival, I have a feeling lots of guests will be appearing from here on like a festival,
とりあえずはね ま、4周年ということで えー皆さんもね え、みなとあくあをね 応援してくれて本当にありがとうございます！
for now though, well, being our 4th-anniversary, um, everyone, um, thank you so much for supporting Minato Aqua!
ありがとう！ いや本当に入ってさんはねめちゃめちゃ本当
Thank you! Seriously, looking back, I really, truly...
こう、短くな…すごいね 本当に皆さんに助けていただいたばかりで
have been helped so much by everyone,
本当にホロメンの皆もそうだしマネージャーさんもそうだしスタッフの皆さんもそうだし
truly, all the Hololive members, the managers, the staff,
何よりもみんなにね なんかこう助けてもらって支えてもらってばかりだけど いやーなんだか感慨深いよ
above all, being helped and supported by everyone so much... man, it's deeply moving.
ね？こうして、なんかよん、4年前はね こう4周年ってなったときに想像してみたんだけど
Right? When I imagined what it'd be like 4 years ago when reaching the 4th anniversary,
なんか4年前 私デビューしたときはさ、こうやってね このフェスティバルとか言ってたくさんのゲストと共にこんな可愛い衣装きて
I never thought when I debuted 4 years ago that I'd be wearing such a cute outfit alongside so many guests at a "festival",
こう歌って踊れるなんて思ってなかったしね！
singing and dancing like this!
初めての3D配信をね この前見かした…見かしたんだけど 本当にねなんかねアイドルらしかなぬね全点とかやってたよ全点
I looked back at my first 3D stream the other day... and honestly, I was doing completely un-idol-like forward rolls and stuff.
でね、あのね骨が折れてた ちょっと黒歴史に近いけど 本当にね
And, you know, my bone broke... It's kind of dark history, but really,
あのときもねちょっとね なんか頑張って踊ってたけど あのところとはね比べ物にならないくらいねダンスが上達しました！上達しました！
back then I danced hard too, but my dancing has improved so much compared to back then! It's improved!
もうね なんか運動、運動不足、運動神経の悪い人の動きだとは言わせない！言わせない！言わせ、言わせないぞ！
You can no longer say I move like someone lacking in exercise or motor skills! No way! Absolutely not!
え？どうかな？結構すんなり、軽やかにいけてるでしょ？でしょ？
Eh? What do you think? I'm going pretty smoothly and lightly, right? Right?
ということでね、えー、ま、4周年で成長もありだけどね、たくさんの成長もありますけど、未だにね運動不足ではありますけど、運動神経はね、やっぱ悪いなとは思いますが
So, um, well, with 4 years there's growth, and though there's lots of growth, I'm still lacking in exercise, and my motor skills are still pretty bad I suppose,
え、4年目も どうぞみんな よろしくお願いしまーーす！
um, for our 4th year too, everyone, please treat me well!
ということで それではここからゲストパート行きたいと思いますが、その前に！
So, now I'd like to move on to the guest part, but before that!
なんと！こんな！あ、このの、アクイシヨウのままじゃ ちょっと なんかさ、浮いちゃうかなって思って ちょっと今から大変身するから見ててねー！へんしーん！
What's more! Like this! Ah, if I stay in this outfit, I thought it might stand out a bit weirdly, so I'm going to transform right now, so watch! Transform!
わーい！ということでいつものアイドル衣装にチェンジしたということで それではこっか…
Yay! So I changed into my usual idol outfit! And now...
どこかで途切れた物語 僕らもう一度その先へ
Don't know where our story was cut off, let's go beyond once more,
たとえ何度離れてしまってもほらつながっている
even if we drift apart many times, look, we're connected.
交わした言葉 あれから幾つ朝日を見たんだ
The words we exchanged, how many mornings have I seen since then?
それぞれの暮らしの先で あの日の続き 再会の日
In our respective lives beyond, the continuation of that day, the day of reunion.
待ち合わせまでの時間がただ 過ぎていく度に胸が高鳴る
As the time until our meeting simply passes by, my heart beats faster.
雨上がりの空見上げれば あの日と同じ様に 架かる七色の橋
Looking up at the sky after the rain, just like that day, a seven-colored bridge appears.
ここでもう一度出会えたんだよ 僕らつながっていたんだずっと
We were able to meet once again right here, we've always been connected.
話したいこと 伝えたいことって 溢れて止まらないから
Things I want to talk about, things I want to tell you overflow and won't stop.
巡る季節に急かされて 続く道のその先また
Urged on by the revolving seasons, further down the continuing road once more.
離れたってさ 何度だってさ 強く結び直したなら また会える
Even if we parted, no matter how many times, if we tie our bonds tightly again, we can meet again.
何だっけ 思い出話は止まらないね 辿った記憶と回想
What was it? Reminiscing stories never end, memories and recollections we traced.
なぞって笑っては 空いた時間を満たす
Tracing and laughing, filling the empty time.
言葉と言葉で気づけば 明日のことは気にせずどうせ
Realizing through words and words, not worrying about tomorrow anyway,
まるで昔に戻ったような 変わってしまったことだって
as if returning to the past, even the things that have changed
本当はきっといくつもある だけど今日だけあの頃のままで
truly surely there are many, but just today we stay as we were back then.
気づけば空は白み始め 疲れていた僕らの片頬に
Before we knew it, the sky began to whiten, against the cheeks of us exhausted ones
触れるほのかな温かさ あの日と同じ様に それぞれの日々に帰る
a faint warmth touches us, just like that day, returning to our respective days.
ねえ ここまで歩いてきた道は それぞれ違うけれど
Hey, the paths we've walked up to here are each different,
同じ朝日に 今照らされてる また重なり合えたんだ
illuminated by the same morning sun right now, we overlapped once more.
どこかで途切れた物語 僕らもう一度その先へ
Don't know where our story was cut off, let's go beyond once more,
話したいこと 伝えたいことって ページを埋めていこうよ
things I want to talk about, things I want to tell you, let's fill in the pages.
ほら 描き出そう何度でも
Look, let's draw it out no matter how many times.
いつか見上げた赤い夕日も
The red setting sun we looked up at someday too,
気づけばそれは調べ初め だから果てた僕らの足音に
Before we knew it, it began to tune, so to the exhausted footsteps of ours
触れるほのかな温かさ あの日と同じ様に
a faint warmth touches, just like that day,
それぞれの日々に変える
returning to our respective days.
ねえ ここまで歩いてきた道は それぞれ違うけど
Hey, the paths we've walked up to here are each different,
同じ朝日に 今照らされてる また重なり合えたんだ
illuminated by the same morning sun right now, we overlapped once more.
どこかで途切れた物語 僕らもう一度その先へ
Don't know where our story was cut off, let's go beyond once more,
話したいこと 伝えたいことって ページを埋めていこうよ
things I want to talk about, things I want to tell you, let's fill in the pages.
ほら 描き出そう何度でも
Look, let's draw it out no matter how many times.
いつか見上げた赤い夕日も
The red setting sun we looked up at someday too,
共に過ごした青い日々も
The blue days we spent together too,
忘れないから 消えやしないから
because we won't forget, because they won't fade away,
緑が芽吹くように また会えるから
like green sprouting, we can meet again.
物語は白い 朝日 から始まる
The story begins from the white morning sun,
「また明日」
“See you tomorrow.”
はい、というわけで！
Yes, and that's why!
ステラテールの2人が来てくれました！ありがとうーー！
The two from Stellatale came! Thank you so much!
おとといぶり。おとといぶりだ、そうだ。
Day before yesterday. Oh right, day before yesterday.
おとといっていうのか？おとといぶりか。
Do you say 'day before yesterday'? Like day before yesterday.
おととい、あれ？なんかさ、また会えたんだね、とか言ってさ。
Day before, huh? Like, 'we met again,' we said.
実はもう会ってましたね、みたいな（笑）
Actually we already met, right? (Laughs)
そう、もう会ってた。フフフ（笑）すいません、先に。
Right, we already met. Hehe (Laughs) Sorry, first.
そう、ね、あくたんのキデミとトワのちょっとセットリストがね、一緒だったっていうことで。
Right, Aqua-tan's Kitemi and Towa's setlists were kind of the same.
そうです、おめでとうございます！おめでとう！
That's right, congratulations! Congratulations!
おめでとうございます！おめでとう！同じ日なんですよ。
Congratulations! Congratulations! It's the exact same day.
あ、すい、すい、ここで共演するっていうの、あくあ先輩が…あはは（笑）
Ah, Sui, Sui, performing together here, Aqua-senpai... Haha (Laughs)
え、いいよ、はい、なんか
Wait, sure, yeah, somehow...
いや実は、本日はお揃いで、お揃いだ！
Actually, today we're matching, we're matching!
きょうきょうきょうきょう、あれ？
Today, today, today, today, huh?
きょう記念日だよね？もしかして
Today's our anniversary, right? Could it be?
あ、衣装、衣装、衣装、衣装、お揃いじゃね？
Ah, outfit, outfit, outfit, outfit, aren't they matching?
あくせんちゃんねる、あくせんちゃんねる
Aksen Channel, Aksen Channel
実はですね、ここで一番最初に思いますよね。
Actually, you'd think something was strange right from the start.
あくせちゃんねるじゃない、あくせちゃんねる
It's not Aksen Channel, Aksen Channel!
一応アンチなんだけど、でも
We're technically antis, but...
今日記念日が一応記念日が
Today's our anniversary, our anniversary is...
一応アンチなんだけどね
We're technically antis, you know.
しかもツインテールも一緒だし、確かにポニーテールだ
Plus our twin tails match too, wait, it's a ponytail.
しかもどっちもクルクルしてやがる
And both of us are all curly!
三人となんかさ、共通点ないのかな、私たち
Don't the three of us have something in common, us three?
三人、三人の共通...共通って
The three of us, what's in common... common...
何んだろうね、ちょっと宿題しようか宿題
I wonder what it is. Let's give homework.
女、女、女！広いじゃんそれ女子
Woman, woman, woman! That's huge, girls!
いつもうかな、でさ、全員メッシュが入ってる
Always, and like, everyone has streaks in their hair.
じゃない？すいちゃんはちょっと、今日は落ちてるんだけど
Right? Suisei-chan is a bit down today though.
今日は落としてるんだけど
She has it down today.
すいちゃんもね、あの別の衣装だったらインナーから入ってるから
Suisei-chan too, you know, in other outfits it's from the inner hair.
あぁそうそう、別の衣装ならね、別の衣装ならね
Ah right, in other outfits, in other outfits.
やっぱね、ちょっとね、ぎこちないスタートでございますけどもね
It's a bit of an awkward start, you know.
ぎこちないわ、ぎこちないです。これからもぎこちなくね
It is awkward. We'll keep being awkward from now on.
やっていきましょう、これからもさ、三人で共通点作ろうね
Let's keep going. Let's make more common points between the three of us.
でも次いつ会えるかわかんないよ。私達もね、揃ったの久しぶりだし
But who knows when we'll meet next. It's been a while since all three of us got together.
久しぶりだからね、三日ぶり、三日ぶり
It's been a while, 3 days, 3 days!
三日ぶりだから、そもそも私たち打ち合わせしてないからね
It's been 3 days, and we didn't even have a meeting beforehand.
確かに、打ち合わせしてないじゃん
True, we didn't have a meeting.
でも二人間なんかさ、焼肉行ったとか言ってなかった？
But didn't you two say you went to yakiniku or something?
あ、そうだ、あ二人でラーメン食べたわ、スイトアチャンネルで
Ah right, the two of us ate ramen at Suito-A Channel!
誰だよ、誰だよ、誰だよ
Who is that, who is that, who is that!
じゃあ次の曲いきましょう、次アンチがいる状態
Well then, let's go to the next song, next is the state with antis.
アンチ、アンチ...
Antis, antis...
ふでペン ふふ、ふるえる ふふ
My calligraphy pen, fufu, is trembling, fufu
初めてキミへの greeting card
As I write my first ever greeting card to you
ときめき passion、あふれて action
My throbbing passion, overflowing action
はみだしちゃうかもね
Might just spurt out
キミの笑顔想像して いいとこ見せたくなるよ
I imagine your smile and want to show you my good points
情熱をにぎりしめ 振り向かせなくちゃ！
I grasp my passion, I gotta make you notice me!
愛をこめてスラスラとね さあ書き出そう
All right, I'm gonna write smoothly with all my love
受け取ったキミに幸せがつながるように
So that me and you can be connected by happiness when received
夢を見せてクルクルとね 字が舞い踊る
I'm showing you my dreams as my characters dance around
がんばれふでペン ここまできたから
Hang in there, calligraphy pen, you've made it this far
かなり本気よ☆
I'm totally serious
ふでペン ふふ、むりかぶく
Calligraphy pen, fufu, pushing it too far
くじけそうになるけれど
It seems I might be crushing it, but
手書きが mission、熱いぜ tension
My handwriting's on a mission, red-hot tension
印刷じゃつまらない
Normal print is so boring
はねるとこ止まるとこ ドキドキまるで恋だね
Where it jumps, where it stops, heart-throbbing is love
これからもヨロシクね 一言そえて
"Please treat me well from here on out," I add that single phrase
はしゃぐ文字はピカピカにね ほら磨き上げ
My cheerful lettering is so shiny, look how well polished
まっすぐキミのココロまで 届けばいいな
It'd be wonderful if it could go straight into your heart
走る軌跡キラキラだね 乾くまで待って
The running lines shine until they dry, you'll have to wait
ふでペン fu fu
Calligraphy pen, fufu
ボールペン fu fu
Ballpoint pen, fufu
おやすみしてて かなり本気よ
Rest easy, I'm totally serious!
かなり本気よ
Totally serious!
キミの笑顔 想像して
Imagining your smile,
いいとこ見せたく なるよ
I want to show you my good side.
情熱を にぎりしめて
Grasping my passion tightly,
振り向かせ なくちゃ！
I've got to make you look my way!
愛をこめて スラスラとね さあ書き出そう
Writing smoothly with all my love, let's start!
受け取った キミにしあわせ がつながるように
So happiness reaches you when you receive it.
夢を見せて クルクルとね 字が舞い踊る
Showing my dreams, characters dance around.
がんばれふでペン ここまできたから かなり本気よ
Hang in there, pen, I'm totally serious!
かなり本気よ
Totally serious!
ゆい…え？今日の一番最高だった！
Yui... Eh? Today's live was the best!
ゆいゆいゆい！
Yui, Yui, Yui!
ゆい最高だったぞ！
Yui, it was the best!
練習の成果だったな！
It was the fruit of practice!
船長、あれ？船長？ゆい…最高だったじゃないか！
Senchou, wait? Senchou? Yui... wasn't it the best?!
K音？な、ゆい…バンドやろうよ！
K-ON? Right, Yui... let's start a band!
バンド！K音部だよ！K音部！
A band! The K-ON club! The K-ON club!
K音部…で、りっちゃん！
The K-ON club... and Ritsu!
りっちゃん？りっちゃんて誰？まりんなんだけど。
Ritsu? Who's Ritsu? It's Marine, you know.
船長？うん、船長なんだけど。
Senchou? Yeah, I'm Senchou.
あれ、りっちゃん…名前忘れないでよもう！待って待って、さっきまでりっちゃん音頭やってたじゃん！
Hey, Ritsu... don't forget my name! Wait, until just now you were doing the Ritsu Ondo!
おいあくたん、船長、さっきからギター、エアギターしすぎでさ…
Hey Akutan, Senchou, you've been playing air guitar so much since earlier...
エアギターじゃなくてさ、買ってから買ってエアギターしちゃったんだけど。
It's not air guitar, I bought it and started playing air guitar.
エアとか言うな！エアじゃないから！
Don't call it air! It's not air!
ちゃんと言ってたじゃんか！
You were playing it properly!
あ、弾いてて気分だったんだ！
Ah, I was just in the mood!
いやでもギター持ってる姿あんまりないからさ、せっかくだから…ちょっと替えてみる？
But since you rarely hold a guitar, let's trade for a bit!
替えてみるか！すごい、ちなみに船長それベースだよ！
Let's trade! By the way Senchou, that's a bass!
これベース？ベースだ！
This is bass?! It's bass!
こうやって引いてるけどベースでこうやってやらないのかな？
You play it like this, but shouldn't you play bass properly?
コードだね、コードだね。あ、こうやってやればよかった！
It's chords, chords. Oh, doing it like this is great!
ちょっとさ、やろうよ。やりそこなったから。
Let's do it a bit. We messed up earlier.
じゃあ、じゃあ見て、激しいこの子の動き。
So, look at this intense movement of hers.
痛い痛い痛い！痛いよ！ぶつかりまくってるって言う。
It hurts! It hurts! It keeps bumping into everything!
痛いよ、肩がボロボロになっちゃう！
It hurts, my shoulder's getting battered!
大丈夫？あくたん、まだ温まれるから！
Are you okay? Aqua, you can still warm up!
あくたん、傷だらけにするの楽しいな！
Aqua, getting all scratched up is fun!
痛いよ、おかしくだろ！いて…
It hurts, that's crazy! Ouch...
いて、怖い怖い怖いって！
Ouch, scary, scary, scary!
あくたん何逃げてんの！怖いって！逃げるな！
Aqua, what are you running away for! It's scary! Don't run!
手が勝手に引いてる…！え、船長ギタリストの才能あるかも！
My hand is playing by itself...! Senchou might have guitarist talent!
これ現実だ、これベースだわ。
This is reality, this is bass.
なんでこの曲選んだの？
Why did you choose this song?
あのね、なんか船長を見ると、K-ONを思い出すっていうか…あくたん、結構鋭い！
Well, when I see Senchou, it reminds me of K-ON... Aqua, you're quite sharp!
鋭い？船長ね、実はね、K-ONと同じ感じで…
Sharp? Senchou, actually, with the same feeling as K-ON...
本当に、なんかYuiたちと一緒に卒業していったまであるレベルで、一緒に時を過ごしてきたの。
Really, up to the level of graduating together with Yui and the others, spending time together.
待って、船長の時代ってK-ONあんの？なにこれ？
Wait, did K-ON even exist in Senchou's era? What is this?
え、これハート！若い、TikTokなやつだ！
Eh, this is a heart! Young, TikTok stuff!
あるよ！ふざけないで！あるよ、K-ONと一緒に時を過ごしてきたって！
It exists! Don't mess with me! We spent time together with K-ON!
もうずっと手が止まらないんだけど！誰か止めて、右手止めて！
My hand won't stop! Someone stop it, stop my right hand!
でもさ、せっかくギター持ったからあくたんに、ギターを使った秘技を教えたいなと思って。
But since we're holding guitars, Aqua, I want to teach you a secret guitar technique.
本当ですか？ちょっと普通に弾き方ずっとやってて、新しい弾き方が今浮かんできた。
Really? I've been playing normally all this time, and a new playing style just came to me.
え、それベースだけどね！そう、これベース！なんでも言うけどさ、聞けよ！
Eh, that's bass though! Right, this bass! Whatever, just listen!
秘技！走り弾き！このまま去っていけ るっていう…
Secret technique! Running-while-playing! You can just walk away like this...
ちょっと待ってあくたん！Yuiちゃんなんてそんなことしないから！待って！
Wait a minute Aqua! Yui-chan would never do that! Wait!
天音かなた
Amane Kanata
湊あくあ
Minato Aqua
泣きべそ ばっかかいてんのは どちら様
Who's the one crying all the time?
笑われた 分だけやり返せ
Pay them back for every time you were laughed at
泣きべそばかりかいてるのはどちら様
Who's the one always crying?
笑われた分だけやり返せ
Fight back as much as you were laughed at.
今に見てろと手にしたものは
The thing you grasped, thinking "Just you wait,"
爆弾やナイフなんて代物じゃないけど
isn't something like a bomb or knife, but...
一切合切今後どうなったって約束しよう
Let's promise, no matter what happens from now on,
背中の値札を引き剥がせ
Rip off the price tag on your back.
廃材みたいな毎日だけれど
Though everyday is like scrap material,
捨てるのはまだ早いだろう
it's still too early to throw it away.
今日も打ち震えながら終点駅のホームで
Today too, trembling on the platform of the last station,
明日人がまだ待っている
tomorrow people are still waiting.
わがままでおとなし主のお出迎えを
To welcome our selfish and quiet master.
どうせ何年経って車が空飛べど
No matter how many years pass and cars fly in the sky,
きっと何年経って機械が喋れども
even if years pass and machines can speak,
何だって言いたいんだ便利って言う前に
whatever you want to say, before calling it convenient,
心の傷口を治してくれ
please heal the wounds in my heart.
あんな空でミサイルが飛ぶのなら
If missiles are flying in a sky like that,
そんなもので幸せを乞うのなら
and if we beg for happiness from such things,
優しい人にならなくちゃ
we have to become kind people.
僕は僕を肯定していけるかな
I wonder if I can keep affirming myself.
頭上げて前向けと言われても
Even if told to lift my head and look forward,
暗闇じゃ前もクソもないな
in the dark there's no front or crap at all.
一人で居れど二人で居れど
Whether alone or with two,
孤独は孤独に変わりゃしねえ
loneliness never changes from being lonely.
死にたいとかそんな歌を歌って
Singing songs about wanting to die,
またそれかと禍を打たれた
and being struck by misfortune once more,
けれどもそれほどのことしか
yet it's only to that extent that
口から零れる言葉がどうしても
the words spilling from my mouth anyhow
見つからないや
cannot be found.
今日の僕はこうして
Today I am like this,
ゲーセンに吸い込まれる
being sucked into the arcade.
明日が来なければいいのにな
I wish tomorrow wouldn't come.
最終列車の汽笛がうるさく響く
The whistle of the last train echoes noisily.
どうせ愛なんてと斜に構えて強がっても
Even if I act tough with a cynical view on love,
きっと本心じゃ寂しさに襲われて
deep down I'm surely seized by loneliness.
現在現状の僕らはそうしようもないな
Right now we are truly helpless.
うるさいなあお前なんて大嫌いだ
How annoying, I hate someone like you.
あんな空でミサイルが飛ぶのなら
If missiles are flying in a sky like that,
そんなもので命が飛ぶのなら
and lives are lost to such things,
優しい人にならなくちゃ
we have to become kind people.
心が孤独と答えを出したって
Even if my heart concludes it's loneliness,
優しい人にならなくちゃ心が勝ち込む前に
we have to become kind people before our hearts give in.
よかったねー！
That was so good!
かなたん来てくれてありがとう！
Kanatan, thank you for coming!
お邪魔します！
Thanks for having me!
いやあ、あくたん、
Man, Aqua-tan,
4周年おめでとうございます！
Happy 4th anniversary!
ありがとうございます！
Thank you so much!
Thank you!
こんなチャンス祝ってもらって、なんかちょっと嬉しいな。
I'm so happy to be celebrated like this.
嬉しいね、なんか。ハキハキしゃべろっか。
It really makes me happy. Let's speak clearly.
いや、あのね、前も私の誕生日の時にも一緒に…
Um, you know, before, for my birthday too, we together...
あ、ええ、ありがとうございました！お誕生日おめでとう。
Ah, yes, thank you so much! Happy birthday.
あの時はですね、あの、MCがいなかったんで。
Back then, you see, um, there was no MC.
あ、そうだっけ？
Ah, was that so?
なぎめあのこうやって喋るのはね。
That's why we were chatting like this.
そう、二人きりではあの、初めましてということで、初めまして、どうも。
That's right, as just the two of us, it's like nice to meet you, hello.
いやあ、私たち、え、あの、今回…
Man, the two of us, um, this time...
なんて呼んでくれたのかな？
I wonder why you invited me?
いや、なんかね、やっぱ、あの、かなたんと、この曲、歌いたいなって思ってたんだよね。
Well, you know, I really wanted to sing this song with Kanatan.
えー、そうなんだ！嬉しい！あの、私たちってね…
Eh, really? I'm so happy! You see, we don't really...
あんまりコラボとかもしてなくてさ。そうだね、本当に。
do collabs together that much. That's right, honestly.
本当にいつしたんだ、最後は。
When was the last time we even did one?
ううん、でも一緒で歌ってから、ねえ、歌ってみたとかも…
Um, but after singing together, you know, like cover songs too...
そうだね、そうなんだ、あんまりしてるの本当にしてないね。
That's right, we really haven't done much at all.
でもほら、最近LINE交換…したよん。
But hey, recently we exchanged LINE addresses...
LINE？
LINE?
しとらん。
We didn't.
LINE交換したやん。
We exchanged LINEs, didn't we?
ショック。
Shocking.
LINE交換したやん、この間。で、それ1回も、やり取りしてないんだけど。
We exchanged LINEs the other day, and we haven't messaged each other even once.
あれ？したっけ？本気で忘れてるんだけど。
Huh? Did we? I honestly forgot.
ちょっと待って、ねえ。
Wait a second, hey.
本当にいつだっけ？
Seriously, when was that?
いや、したよ！したよ！
No, we did! We did!
え、待って待って、いつ？いつしたっけ？
Wait, wait, when? When did we?
え、何、え、何があった？何、どこにね、仲人に赴き ですが、いざという時にちゃんとLINEやってたから、え、あくも、みんなあって言ったら、
Wait, what, what happened? Where did we go... wait, since we properly used LINE when it mattered, uh, when Akumo said everyone is here,
やったー！本気で忘れてるんですけど。
Yay! I seriously forgot.
そうだ。この、このMC3分ぐらいあるんだけど、まだ、まだ時間あるんだけど、
That's right. This, this MC is about 3 minutes long, but we still have time,
これから僕たちの関係性が始まっていくってことで、
and since our relationship is just starting from now on,
現時点でアクタンの中の僕がどこにいるのかちょっと聞きたいんですけど、
I want to ask where I currently stand inside Aktan.
あ、ここが、あの、知り合い。知り合い。なるほどね。
Ah, here is, um, acquaintance. Acquaintance. I see.
知り合い、知り合い。ええ、仕事仲間。
Acquaintance, acquaintance. Uh, work colleague.
仕事仲間。友達。友達。
Work colleague. Friend. Friend.
大親友。
Best friend.
待って、フレアはすごくない？
Wait, Flare is amazing, right?
どこですか？その間、間、間にいれてもいいよ。
Where is she? You can put her in-between.
いや、大親友は、めちゃくちゃ大親友じゃん。
No, best friend is like, super best friend.
なんでも相談できる、毎日連絡を取る、大親友。
Someone you can consult about anything, keep in touch with every day, a best friend.
まあ、まあね。うん。
Well, yeah. Yeah.
ですね。ええ、大親友やりたい、やりたいって感じです。
Right. Um, I want to be best friends, that's the feeling.
仕事仲間… がんこな… がんこな…
Work colleague... Stubborn... stubborn...
なんか、時々来るんだよね、こういうパンチ、パンチ来るんだよ。
Like, sometimes she hits me with these punches, punches come at me.
いや、でもこっからね、大親友に近づいていくんで、
Well, but from here, we're getting closer to being best friends,
ぶっちゃけ今のいまは、まあ、そうだな、船長の友達。
to be honest, right now, well, yeah, the Captain's friend.
友達の友達。
A friend's friend.
あ、でもこ、こっからはまりんがいないとなんか、こっからね、やっぱ衣装なんかもちょっと、
Ah, but from her, without Marine, like, from here, you know, the outfits also...
なんか、ついに、ついにになってるような、色が。
Like, it's finally, finally becoming... the colors.
すごいよね、これ。
It's amazing, right? This.
ちょっと双子なんで。
Since we're like twins.
そうなの！でも真逆になってる。
That's right! But we're opposites.
じゃあ最後にアクタン、僕に愛情をいっぱい込めて抱きついてもらって終わりにしましょう。
Well then, finally, Aktan, please hug me with lots of affection and let's end it.
なんて友達の友達なのに！そうだよ、ここで友達がいないっていう壁を破るんだ！
Why a friend's friend?! That's right, break down the wall of having no friends here!
おいで！おいで！抱きついたー！
Come here! Come here! Hugged!
袖丈が覚束ない夏の終わり
What length sleeve to wear at the end of summer
明け方の電車に揺られて
Knocked around by the train at dawn
思い出した 懐かしいあの風景
I remembered that one view, so familiar
たくさんの遠回りを繰り返して
Again and again, I took so many detours
同じような街並みが ただ通り過ぎた
Similar city streets simply whizzing by
窓に僕が映ってる
In the window I see myself
君は今もあの頃みたいにいるのだろうか
Are you still the way you were back then?
ひしゃげて曲がった あの自転車で走り回った
You rode around on your bike, all squashed and bent
君はいまもあの頃みたいにいるのだろうか
Are you still the way you were back then?
ひしゃげて曲がった あの自転車で走り回った
You rode around on your bike, all squashed and bent
馬鹿々しい縄跳び 膝に滲んだ血
A foolish balancing act, blood staining my knees
今はなんだかひどく虚しい
Right now it all feels horribly empty
どれだけ背丈が変わろうとも 変わらない何かがありますように
However much my height might change, I hope some things will stay the same
くぐらない影に励まされ 今も歌う 今も歌う 今も歌う
Comforted by silly little traces of things, to this day I sing, still sing, still sing
ラララ…
Lalala...
忙しく街を走るタクシーに
In a taxi racing hurriedly through the city
ぼんやりと背負われたまま くしゃみをした
Spacing out as it takes me somewhere, I sneezed
窓の外を眺める
I gaze out the window
袖丈が覚束ない夏の終わり
Not sure what length sleeve to wear at summer's end,
明け方の電車に揺られて
rocked around by the train at dawn.
思い出した 懐かしいあの風景
That's when I remembered that familiar scenery.
たくさんの遠回りを繰り返して
Taking so many detours over and over,
同じような街並みが ただ通り過ぎた
similar city streets simply passed me by.
窓に僕が写ってる
I see myself reflected in the window.
君は今も あの頃みたいにいるのだろうか
Are you still living like you did back then?
靴を片方 茂みに落として探し回った
You lost a shoe in the bushes and searched all around.
何があろうと 僕らはきっと 上手くいくと
Whatever happens, we're sure to do well,
無邪気に笑えた 日々を憶えている
remembering the days we laughed so innocently.
どれだけ無様に傷つこうとも 終わらない毎日に花束を
However clumsily we get hurt, a bouquet to days that never end.
くららない面影を追いかけて
Chasing after those foolish traces,
今も歌う 今も歌う 今も歌う
I'm still singing, still singing, still singing.
朝日が昇る前の欠けた月も 君もどこかでで見ているかな
The waning moon before sunrise—are you somewhere out there looking at it too?
何故か訳もないのに胸が痛くて 滲む顔霞む色
For no reason my chest hurts; a blurring face, hazy colors.
今更悲しいと叫ぶには あまりに全てが遅すぎたかな
Is it far too late now to cry out in sadness?
もう一度初めから歩けるなら すれ違うように君に会いたい
If I could walk it all over again, I'd want to meet you like we're passing by.
どれだけ背中が変わろうとも 変わらない 何かがありますように
However much our backs may change, I hope something remains unchanged.
くららない面影に励ましを 今も歌う 今も歌う 今も歌う
Comforted by those foolish traces, I'm still singing, still singing, still singing.
朝日が昇る前の欠けた月も 君もどこかでで見ているかな
The waning moon before sunrise—are you somewhere out there looking at it too?
何もないと笑える朝日がきて 始まりは青い色
An ordinary morning comes where we can smile; the beginning is a shade of blue.
始まりは青い色
The beginning is a shade of blue.
あくあ！ 4周年おめでとう！
Aqua! Happy 4th anniversary!
ありがとうおかゆ！ありがとう！
Thank you, Okayu! Thank you!
ということでおかゆが来てくれました！
And so, Okayu came to join us!
いや今回もね呼んでくれてありがとう！
Yeah, thanks for inviting me again this time!
いやいやいやいや、おかゆさんとはね、やっぱ、運命共同体ですから。
No, no, no, you and I are comrades in destiny, after all!
ああ、そうだったんだ。
Ah, is that so?
呼ばないわけがないわけで。
There's no way I wouldn't invite you!
運命共同体になったつもりは微塵もなかったけどね。
I didn't feel like we became comrades in destiny at all, though.
なんで！そんなことないでしょ！あくおかは永遠だよ！永遠！
Why! That's not true! Aqua and Okayu are eternal! Eternal!
あくおかは永遠？
Aqua and Okayu are eternal?
そうだったんだ。そうだったんだって何さ。
Is that so? What do you mean "is that so"?
そうだったんだ。そうことみたいじゃん。
So that's how it is. It's like that.
いやあ、あくおかはね、むしろなんか、全然そういうのとはかけ離れてる存在だばかりと思ってたけどね。
Well, I actually thought Aqua and Okayu were far removed from that kind of thing.
いやいや、私たちはSとMで繋がってるんで、磁石のように。
No, no, we're connected by S and M, like magnets!
そう、ちょっとキモいね。
Right, that's a bit creepy.
なんで！なんで！なんで！
Why! Why! Why!
なんかがあくおか画Sってこと？そうだよ。でおかゆ、おかゆがM。
What, does Aqua mean S? That's right. And Okayu is M.
逆でもいいよ。なんかちょっと怖い、距離離れ立ってきた。
Either way is fine though. Somehow it's getting a bit scary, keeping our distance.
なんでさ！なんだよ！まあまあまあまあ、ちょっと、これ気持ち悪くなっちゃうからさ。
Why is that! Well, well, well, since this is getting a bit weird...
はい、灰色と青ね、エモかったね。
Yeah, "Haiiro to Ao" was emotional, right?
気持ち悪くないけどね。大切だけどね。
It wasn't weird though! Though it's precious!
いやよかったね。めっチャめちゃよかったよ！
Yeah, it was great. It was super, super great!
やっぱり、ちょっと今年のあくおかは、2022年バージョンは、ちょっとエモ路線で行きたいんですよ。
As expected, for this year's Aqua and Okayu, the 2022 version, we want to go with an emotional route.
ああ、みなとプロデューサー的には！あくおかはエモ...
Ah, from Minato Producer's perspective! Aqua and Okayu are emo...
エモいです。 エモしか無いです、やっぱ。
Emo, right?
エモしか無いです、やっぱ。
There's nothing but emo, really.
いや、僕たちどっちかっていうと逆みたいな感じなとこない?
Well, isn't our dynamic kind of the opposite?
ないよ。
No way.
私たちは永遠ラブストーリーコメディー!
We're an eternal love story comedy!
いやいやいやいや、いやもうコメディー言うてもうてますやん!
Yeah, yeah, yeah! You're already calling it a comedy!
いやいやいやいや。
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
いやー、そうか。オフィスラブ…
Right, "office love"... Oh.
オフィスラブ! オフィスラブ!
Office love! Office love!
そう!だから、今日はおかゆが来てくれたから、このステージでちょっとふたりきりで、最後星を眺めながらエンディングっていうね。
That's right! Since Okayu came today, we're gonna look at the stars together and do our ending!
あ、そうだそうだ、そろそろね、みんなのこと呼びに行かなきゃいけない時間じゃん。
Right, right, soon we should go call everyone.
いやいや待って待って待って待って。
Wait, wait, wait, wait!
空を見ながら星を眺めてエンディングって…。
While looking at the sky and gazing at the stars, for the ending...
みんなー!
Everyone!
そろそろ準備の時間だよー!
It's almost time to get ready!
待って!
Wait!
おかゆー!
Okayu!
人が溢れた交差点をどこへ行く?
At an intersection full of people, where are you going?
(押し流され)
Worn out by the push of the crowd...
似たような服を着て 似たような表情で…
Woring similar clothes with similar expressions...
群れの中に紛れるように 歩いている
Walking as if blending into the crowd.
(疑わずに)
(Without question)
誰かと違うことに何をためらうのだろう
What makes you hesitate to be different from others?
先行く人が振り返り 列を乱すなと
The people ahead look back and say not to break the line,
ルールを説くけれど その目は死んでいる
explaining the rules, but their eyes are dead.
君は君らしく生きて行く自由があるんだ
You have the freedom to live your life your own way.
大人たちに支配されるな
Don't let adults control you.
初めから そう諦めてしまったら 僕はなんのために生まれたのか
If we give up from the very start, what were we born for?
夢を見ることは時には孤独にもなるよ
Sometimes dreaming can be lonely,
誰もいない道を進むんだ
walking down an empty road.
この世界は群れていても始まらない
The world doesn't start just because people gather.
Yesでいいのか? サイレントマジョリティー
Is a "Yes" really okay? Silent Majority.
どこかの国の大統領が言っていた
The president of some country said...
(曲解して)
(distorted)
声を上げない者たちは 賛成していると…
that those who don't speak up are in favor of it.
選べる事が大事なんだ 人に任せるな
Choosing is important, don't leave it to others.
行動しなければ Noと伝わらない
If you don't act, "No" won't be communicated.
君は君らしくやりたいことをやるだけさ One of themに成り下がるな
You just have to live your life your own way, don't be reduced to just one of them.
ここにいる人の数だけ 道はある
There are as many paths as there are people here.
自分の夢の方に 歩けばいい
Just walk toward your own dreams.
見栄やプライドの 鎖に繋がれたような つまらない大人手置いてゆけ
Leave behind boring adults bound by chains of vanity and pride.
さあ未来は君たちのためにある
Come on, the future is for you.
Noと言おう!
Say "No!"
サイレントマジョリティー
Silent Majority.
誰かのあと ついいてゆけば 傷つかないけど
If you follow someone else, you won't get hurt,
その群れが 総意だと 一まとめにされる
but that crowd is grouped together as consensus.
君は君らしく生きて行く自由があるんだ
You have the freedom to live your life your own way.
大人たちに支配されるな
Don't let adults control you.
初めから そう諦めてしまったら 僕はなんのために生まれたのか
If we give up from the very start, what were we born for?
夢を見ることは時には孤独にもなるよ 誰もいない道を進むんだ
Sometimes dreaming can be lonely, walking down an empty road.
この世界は群れていても始まらない
This world doesn't start even if we're in a crowd.
Yesでいいのか? サイレントマジョリティー
Is a "Yes" really okay? Silent Majority.
誰かのあと ついてゆけば 傷つかないけど
If you follow someone else, you won't get hurt,
その群れが 総意だと 一まとめにされる
but that crowd is grouped together as consensus.
君は君らしく生きて行く自由があるんだ
You have the freedom to live your life your own way.
大人たちに支配されるな
Don't let adults control you.
初めから そう諦めてしまったら 僕はなんのために生まれたのか
If we give up from the very start, what were we born for?
夢を見ることは時には孤独にもなるよ 誰もいない道を進むんだ
Sometimes dreaming can be lonely, walking down an empty road.
この世界は群れていても始まらない
This world doesn't start even if we're in a crowd.
Yesでいいのか? サイレントマジョリティー
Is a "Yes" really okay? Silent Majority.
君は君らしく生きて行く自由があるんだ
You have the freedom to live your life your own way.
大人たちに支配されるな
Don't let adults control you.
初めから そう諦めてしまったら 僕はなんのために生まれたのか
If we give up from the very start, what were we born for?
夢を見ることは時には孤独にもなるよ 誰もいない道を進むんだ
Sometimes dreaming can be lonely, walking down an empty road.
この世界は群れていても始まらない
This world doesn't start even if we're in a crowd.
Yesでいいのか? サイレントマジョリティー
Is a "Yes" really okay? Silent Majority.
人が溢れた交差点 どこへ行く?
Where are you going in the crowded intersection?
似たような服を着て 似たような表情で
Wearing similar clothes, with similar expressions...
群れの中に紛れるように 歩いている
Walking as if blending into the crowd
誰かと違うことに 何をためらうのだろう
What are you hesitating about, being different?
先行く人が振り返り 列を乱すなと
The people ahead look back, telling you not to break the line
ルールを説くけれど その目は死んでいる
They preach the rules, but their eyes are dead
君は君らしく生きて行く 自由があるんだ
You have the freedom to live your life as yourself
大人たちに支配されるな
Don't let the adults control you
海想列車 ほんの少しだけ
Kaishou Ressha, just a little bit
夢の中で ユラユラ揺られて
Swaying gently inside a dream
波に包まれていたい
I want to be wrapped in the waves
夢を見ていた あの頃の夢を
I was dreaming, the dream of those days
臆病だった どこにも行けなかった
I was cowardly, I couldn't go anywhere
変わりたくて 電車に乗り込んだ
Wanting to change, I boarded the train
この世界で一枚だけの切符
The only ticket in this world
路線図も時刻表も
Even the route map and timetable
今は空白だけど
Are blank now, but
窓の向こうには 青より青い水平線
Beyond the window is a horizon bluer than blue
海想列車 ほんの少しだけ 怖いけれど 走り出した夢はもう止まらない
Kaishou Ressha, just a little scary, but the dream I started running won't stop
正解なんて考えてみてもわからないから 目の前広がるこの景色を見ていたい
I don't know the correct answer even if I think about it, so I want to see this scenery
夢を見ていた あの頃の夢を
I was dreaming, the dream of those days
一人じゃきっと ここまで来れなかった
Alone, I surely couldn't have come this far
途中の駅で 降りたその時も 君がいつも傍にいてくれた
Even when I got off at a station along the way, you were always by my side
「ごめんね」も「ありがとう」も まだ言い足りないよ
I still haven't said "I'm sorry" or "Thank you" enough
私のペースで 不器用なりに伝えてくから
I'll convey it in my own clumsy pace
海峡を走り抜け まだ知らない世界へ 空白の路線図は 今この手で作り上げていく
Running through the straits to an unknown world, I'll create the blank route map with these hands
海想列車 夢から覚めた 懐かしくて 変わらない想いをそっと抱きしめた
Kaishou Ressha, waking from a dream, I softly embraced those nostalgic, unchanging feelings
笑い合って 手を取り合って 同じ時間を過ごした君とこれからもずっと
Smiling together, holding hands, with you who spent the same time, always from now on
海想列車 もう怖くはない 無我夢中で駆け抜けた日々は 夢じゃないから
Kaishou Ressha, I'm no longer scared, the days I ran through in a trance are not a dream
世界なんて相変わらずまだ分からないけど 目の前にある色づくこの景色を見ていたい
I still don't understand the world, but I want to see this colorful scenery before my eyes
会う 君と一緒に この景色を見ていたい
I want to see this scenery together with you
ということでありがとうございましたー！
So, thank you very much!
えー、海藻列車でした。ありがとうございました。
Um, that was "Kaisou Ressha." Thank you very much.
海藻列車はね、3周年の記念で出させていただいた曲なんだけど、
"Kaisou Ressha" is a song I released for my 3rd anniversary, you see,
今回は4周年ということで、
and this time, since it's the 4th anniversary,
今回はちょっと、あくあ色のフェスティバルということで、
this time, as an "Aqua-colored Festival,"
ちょっとですね、たくさんのゲストさんを呼んで、
um, I invited a lot of guests, and
多分こんなにたくさんのゲストを呼ぶのは私のライブでは何げ初めてかな？
inviting this many guests is probably a first for my live concert, I guess?
4周年ということで、先輩だし、いろんな人呼んでわちゃわちゃフェスティバルみたいにできたらいいなと、
Since it's the 4th anniversary, as a senior, I wanted to invite various people and make it like a bustling festival,
いつもと違うかっこいい曲も歌わせていただきました。ありがとう！
so I got to sing some cool songs unlike my usual. Thank you!
みんなと絡めたのもすごい楽しかった。
Interacting with everyone was really fun.
みんなはどうだった？どれがよかったですか？
How about you guys? Which one was good?
なんとここで新曲披露させていただきます！新曲です！
Surprisingly, I will premiere a new song right here! It's a new song!
8月の8日は本当は私のデビュー日、4周年記念なんですが、
August 8th is actually my debut date, my 4th anniversary, but
その8月8日に先行ストリーミング配信が始まった新曲「まだ、青い」のライブ初披露です！
it's the live premiere of the new song "Mada, Aoi," released for streaming on August 8th!
今回は新曲を披露させていただこうと思っておるのですが、
I was thinking of premiering the new song this time, but
この配信の後に、なんと新曲「まだ青い」のMVが上がります！
after this stream, amazingly, the MV for "Mada, Aoi" will be released!
マジで凄いので、配信終わったらぜひチェックしてください！おねがいします！
It's seriously amazing, so please check it out after the stream! Please!
クオリティにびっくりすると思う。無料で見てしまっていいの！？ってなるくらい！
You'll be surprised at the quality. It's like "Is it really okay to watch this for free?!"
ぜひ見てください！お願いします！
Please check it out! Please!
そして4周年記念グッズも販売しておりますので、
And 4th anniversary commemorative goods are also on sale,
概要欄で購入できるのでチェックしてください！お願いします！
so you can purchase them via the description box, please check it out! Please!
いろいろグッズになってます！お願いします！
Various items have become goods! Please!
では早速、新曲を歌わせていただきます。聞いてください。「まだ、青い」
Well then, right away, I'll sing the new song. Please listen. "Mada, Aoi"
未だ、青い
Still blue,
風、ひとつ 染まっていく音をたなびかせて
wind, one, letting the dyed sound flutter,
流れ出す 朝焼けの空を飛んでいく
flowing out, flying across the morning sky,
聞こえた 震えてる声の君は誰だろう
I heard, who is the trembling voice?
なんかでかな 会いたくなったんだ 会えるかな
why did I come to want to see you, can I meet you?
夢、ひとつ 鞄のポケットに忍ばせて
dream, one, hide it in the pocket of your bag,
鐘、ひとつ 始まりの朝に遠く響く
bell, one, resound far in the morning of the beginning,
思い出す 結んだ指に残った温度は 今もまだ 青く残っている 褪せぬまま
remembering, the temperature left on the bound fingers remains blue even now without fading,
「鳥や、雲じゃないから 飛んでいくのは、無理だね」
"Since it's not a bird or cloud, flying away is impossible, huh?"
それだったら 歩き出してみよう
If that's the case, let's start walking,
そうやって 描いた今日を通り越して 明日はもっと 君のそばへ
that's how, passing through the drawn today, tomorrow is closer to you.
前へ、そう前へ
Forward, yes, forward,
少しずつ進んでく
moving forward little by little.
一歩、五十歩、百歩踏み出して
Taking one step, fifty steps, a hundred steps,
揺らめいてる君が
you, who are wavering,
青く滲む、青く滲む綺麗に
bleed blue, bleed blue so purely.
会いに行く、会いに行こう今すぐ
I'm going to see you, let's go see you right now.
波白く、さざめく音に耳を立てて
Listening closely to the white, murmuring waves,
赤く、青く、夕映えの空 昇る星
red and blue, a star rising in the twilight sky.
不思議と、不安な旅も怖くないから
Strangely, even an uneasy journey isn't scary,
手を振って、うつむかないように歩いてく
so I wave my hand and walk on without looking down.
「憧れても、願っても 誰にもなれないな」
"Even if I yearn, even if I wish, I can't become anyone."
それだったら 自分になってみよう
If that's the case, let's try becoming ourselves.
そうやって描いた今日を飛び越えて 明日はきっと会えるから
Leaping past the day I envisioned like that, I'm sure we can meet tomorrow.
じゃあね、そうしたらね 一緒に何を話そう
So, when that happens, what shall we talk about together?
一歩、五十歩、百歩重ね合って
Piling up one, fifty, one hundred steps,
紡いでいく時間が溶けていく溶けていく
the time we weave together melts away, melts away.
それでもいつかは 夢が終わるなら
Even so, if someday the dream must end,
それでも良いかな 君がいるなら 世界の中で
even so, would that be okay, if you are here in this world?
出会えた君が 理由になったら それでも良いかな
If the you I met became the reason, would that still be okay?
一人の今日を飛び越えて 描いた今日を通り越して
Leaping past a solitary today, bypassing the day I drew,
明日はもっと君のそばへ
tomorrow I'll go closer to your side.
前へ、そう前へ 少しずつ進むよ
Forward, yes, forward, advancing little by little.
一歩、五百歩、千歩 繰り返して
Repeating one, five hundred, one thousand steps,
指に触れる君が
you, whom my fingers touch,
青く滲む、青く滲む綺麗に
bleed blue, bleed blue so purely.
いつまでもそばにいて 良いかな
Can I stay by your side forever?
良いかな
Would that be okay?
何をしても不器用で 何かとミスばっか
Clumsy at everything I do, making mistakes all the time,
ダメダメな私だって できることがあるの
even a good-for-nothing like me has things she can do.
へこんで悲しくたって 笑顔にしてあげるんだ
When you're down and sad, I'll make you smile,
ここにいるから早く 私を見つけてね
because I'm right here, so find me quickly!
Love you, love you, I love you...
なでなでして...
Pat-pat me...
I love you so much. なでなでして
I love you so much, pat-pat me.
愛して もっと いつでもとなり にいるし
Love me even more, I'm always by your side.
いつでも一緒に笑える 私をたくさんして
Always able to laugh together, make me do it a lot,
たくさん好きして言って
and say you love me a lot.
わがままで朝も苦手 どじでダメダメだけど
Selfish and bad mornings, clumsy and no good, but
それでも私のことを見ててね
even so, please look at me.
描く夢の未来へ続く道を 君と歩けますように
May I walk with you on the road leading to the future of the dreams we draw.
ねぇ もっと好きになってもらいたいのに
Hey, even though I want you to love me even more,